Guide to the American Society of Civil Engineers, Duke University Chapter Records 1932 - 1983 (bulk 1944-1970) UA.31.14.0003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
American Society of Civil Engineers, Duke University Chapter records
1932-1983, bulk 1944-1970
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
American Society of Civil Engineers. Duke University chapter
UA.31.14.0003
2.5 Linear Feet
The Duke University chapter of the American Society of Civil Engineers is an academic group for Engineering students at Duke University, formed in 1932. Records contain correspondence, annual reports, meeting announcements, planning materials for the Engineers Show, a newsletter, minutes, membership lists, membership certificates, photographs, and clippings. Major subjects include the American Society of Civil Engineers, Duke University, the School of Engineering, civil engineering study and teaching, professional development, student societies, and the history of civil engineering. Materials range in date from 1932 to 1983 (bulk 1944-1970). English.
2,500 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The American Society of Civil Engineers, Duke University Chapter Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1973 and 1974.
Historical Note
The Duke University chapter of the American Society of Civil Engineers was formed in 1932 as the Duke Society of Civil Engineers. The group petitioned to join the American Society of Civil Engineers as a student chapter, and in 1933 the society became known as the Duke Student Chapter of the American Society of Civil Engineers. The society was open to any undergraduate student interested in engineering.
The purpose of the student chapter was to further interest in the theory and practice of civil engineering. The chapter held meetings, showed movies, sponsored conferences and exhibitions, took field trips, and invited professionals to speak on campus. Meetings covered a variety of subjects including military tactics, bridges, boating, and air flow systems. The chapter's movie committee worked with industry professionals to gain access to engineering-related films. Many of these correspondences led to speakers visiting Duke University. The society has also sponsored Engineering Shows, which showcased industry design, held contests for student exhibitions, and opened laboratories for viewing projects in progress. Each fall, students took a weekend trip off campus to talk with engineering professionals and tour cutting-edge structures.
As of 2003, the Duke University chapter of the American Society of Civil Engineers is active in the Edmund T. Pratt Jr. School of Engineering.
Collection Overview
Contains correspondence, annual reports, notes from field trips, photographs, and other materials pertaining to the activities of the Duke University student chapter of the American Society of Civil Engineers from 1932 to 1983 (bulk 1944-1970).
Related Material
School of Engineering records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Civil Engineering -- History; Civil Engineering -- Study and teaching -- North Carolina -- Durham; Civil Engineering -- North Carolina; Clippings (information artifacts); Civil Engineering -- Vocational guidance; Photographs; American Society of Civil Engineers; American Society of Civil Engineers. Duke University chapter; Duke University. School of Engineering; Duke University -- Students -- Societies, etc.
- Correspondence, 1950-1970.
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains correspondence between the chapter and the national organization, Duke University departments, other student chapters, and potential speakers.
  Arrangement note
  Ordered by date.
  - 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Annual reports, 1932-1969
  Contains the annual reports of the Duke University chapter, as reported to the headquarters of the American Society of Civil Engineers. Annual reports generally included a calendar of events, a written self-evaluation, lists of members, minutes, clippings and press, notes from field trips, statistical summaries, project and conference reports, and photographs.
  - 1932-1936 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 1938-1944 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - 1951-1954 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - 1961 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - 1963 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Engineering Shows, 1953-1966
  Contains planning materials, announcements, correspondence, proposed building layouts, evaluations, and reports of conferences held at Duke University. The conferences, organized by the chapter, presented awards for excellence in engineering around the United States, held contests for student exhibitions, and opened laboratories for viewing projects in progress.
  - 1953 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - 1954 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - 1955 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - 1956 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - 1957 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - 1958 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - 1959 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - 1960 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - 1962, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Field trips, 1951-1969
  Contains correspondence, itineraries, reports, and photographs from fall field trips.
  - Carolina Steel and Iron Company, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Lone Star Cement Corporation, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - ASCE National Conference, New Orleans, La., 1952 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Nantahala Powerhouse and ASCE National Conference, Atlanta, Ga., 1954 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Kerr Dam, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Washington, D.C. and Baltimore, Md., 1956 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Charlotte, N.C. area plants, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Snake Island Fishway and Ft. McNair College, Washington, D.C. Area, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Washington, D.C. and Baltimore, Md., 1960 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, Kempsville Nike site, Norfolk, Va., 1961 and Carolina Steel Corporation, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 43)
- Chapter establishment, history, and general materials, 1951-1983
  Contains general materials of the Duke University chapter, including histories, minutes, constitutions, photographs, and clippings.
  - Duke University chapter constitutions, ca. 1951 and 1954 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Chapter history, undated (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Chapter ratings, 1956-1963 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Meeting announcements, undated, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Minutes, 1944-1945, 1956, 1962, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Membership and officer lists, 1960-1965 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Membership certificates, undated (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Film committee, advertisements and correspondence, 1951-1953 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Film committee, advertisements and correspondence, 1954-1960 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Order of Saint Patrick, constitution and emblem sketch, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - The Grapevine, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Photographs, 1946, 1951, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Photographs, 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Clippings, 1940-1962, undated (Box 5, Folder 57)